A Guide to the Photographs, Series 1011-1081 FA438
Rockefeller Archive Center
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA), 1946-1968, n.d.; 1027; 6.2 Cubic Feet 19 boxes.
  - Brazil, 2
    - ACAR, Eloi Mendes, Agriculture, Prints: 3 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      1. Spraying pastures for chemical weed control. Agronomist Zalder Araujo of the Associacao de Credito e Assistencia Rural (ACAR) demonstrates to cattle farmer Joao Bemardez and son how to use the new sprayer purchased from loan funds under the supervised credit programs. 2. Agronomist for the Associacao de Credito e Assistencia Rural at Eloi Mendes, Minas Gerais, Brazil, shows farmer how to survey field for terracing to control soil erosion. ACAR lends equipment to farmers until they can afford to buy their own. 3. Demonstration by ACAR staff member at Eloi Mendres, Minas Gerais. ACAR urges farmers to spray and vaccinate cattle, improve pastures and provide supplementary feed which help raise production.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Program, Administration, Prints: 4 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      1. Directors of Companhia Itau and ACAR technicians. 2. ACAR personnel at lunch. 3. ACAR personnel, including six ACAR trainees and two IFYE's. 4. In the ANCAR central office at Belo Horizonte, Miss Aleta McDowell, head of the ACAR home economics department, explains to ANCAR trainees some of the problems of her section. The trainees are (in clockwise order, starting at left) Jose Torres de Menezes, Armando Carneiro da Rocha Filho.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Program, Agriculture, Prints: 2 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      5. No caption. 6. Dr. Penha of Instituto Biologico works with AIA in helping to control animal disease. These pigs with paralysis were sent to his laboratory for study.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Program, Crafts, Prints: 3 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      7. Wives of farm workers and quarries at Fazenda Nova Granja in Minas Gerais, Brazil, take a lesson in laying out a dress pattern from home supervisor Mairana Leite Pinto. Sewing is one of several activities conducted in the ACAR supervised health and education program inaugurated by the farm's management to improve life for its tenant families. 8. Miss Aleta McDowell, US specialist in home economics and head of that section for ACAR in Minas Gerais, makes a regular supervisory visit to the Itau factory's community center where classes are given in nutrition, sewing, child care, gardening and other aids to better living. ACAR supervises the running of the program and trains Brazilian personnel to handle the job; the factory provides buildings and funds. 9. No caption.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Program, Education/Schools, Prints: 8 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      10. This rural school at Fazenda Nova Granja, outlying Belo Horizonte, capital city of Minas Gerais, Brazil, is the center of a new type educational and health program being conducted by the farm management working under the guidance of ACAR. 11. Mariana Leite Pinto, home economics instructor, gives a cooking demonstration in Minas Gerais, Brazil, where ACAR supervises a community-wide health and education program for over 100 farm families. 12. Home supervisor Mariana Leite Pinto conducts story telling hour for pre school children as part of the ACAR guided community health and education program at Fazenda Nova Granja in Minas Gerais, Brazil. 13. Children of farm and quarry workers sing nursery songs and look at picture books in the ACAR guided pre-school program at Fazenda Nova Granja where limestone is mined for the company's cement plant in nearby Belo Horizonte. 14. 180 children of farm workers and quarries, between seven and 11 years of age, attend the rural school at Fazenda Nova Granja in Minas Gerais, Brazil. An ACAR supervised community health and education program was started here last year - has already improved attendance, work habits and interest in school activities. 15. No caption. 16. Pre-School children meet five mornings a week for breakfast, games, and a session of teeth brushing and hair combing at the community center of the Itau cement industry in Minas Gerais. The factory provides funds for this program which teaches better living practices to both children and adults through community center activities and home visiting services; ACAR organized the program, trained Brazilian girls to carry it out, and continues regular, overall supervision of the work, ACAR finds this one way to extend its aid to families despite its own budget limitations. 17. No caption.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Program, Gardening, Prints: 4 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      18. In the school garden at Fazenda Nova Granja, which supplies food for a daily lunch, boys learn proper methods of vegetable growing. Several have started their own gardens at home and set a useful example to their parents in cultivation practices and nutrition. 19. The Itau community garden is cultivated by neighborhood boys, so that families can purchase vegetables cheaply and get free seedlings to start vegetables and new recipes for preparing them. This has brought about improvements in the diet of many families at Itau. 20. School vegetable garden at Fazenda Nova Graja where ACAR is providing guidance for a community wide health and education program. 21. No caption.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Program, Hygiene, Prints: 2 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      22. Children of farm workers at Fazenda Nova Granja learn rudiments of hygiene in their pre-school program recommended by ACAR which is supervising the community-wide health and education effort. 23. Young women of Fazenda Nova Granja, at work in the modernized school kitchen, follow ACAR instructions above washbasin for efficient, sanitary cleaning of plates used for children's lunch. Working with the farm management, ACAR guided renovation of the entire school building and re-planning of the curriculum to produce better trained, healthier young citizens of Brazil.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Program, Miscellaneous, Prints: 7 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      24. A typical small-farm home, where no outside help is received. 25. Now what? Tot tries to decide between pacifier and corn pudding at a supplementary feeding session at the Itau cement factory community center in Minas Gerais. Factory management provided funds for ACAR to set up two community centers and a home visiting service for is 150 worker families. ACAR trained two young Brazilian women to carry on the daily program and continues to give overall technical guidance. 26. Less than years ago most of these children of laborer families in the Itau cement factory in Minas Gerais were thin, listless, and shy. They are rapidly improving in health and vitality by taking part in a community center program including supplementary feeding, games and guidance in personal hygiene. The factory provides funds for the program which was organized by ACAR. 27. This youngster is one of the sixty who turn up five days a week at the community center at the Itau cement factory for breakfast, hygiene lessons and games. ACAR supervises this program aimed to improve the living conditions of the 150 families in the settlement; the factory provides funds for operation expenses and personnel. 28. No caption. 29. No caption. 30. No caption.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Program, Nutrition, Prints: 4 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      31. A supplementary meal with milk is provided at the Itau rural school attended by children of farm and quarry workers. Over 280 children take part in the school and pre-school activities which have brought about increase in weight, generally better health and a lessening of timidity in most of the children. 32. Supplementary meal is provided at the rural school of Fazenda Nova Granja to give children nourishment for growth. Vegetables for meal are grown by the children themselves in the school garden. 33. Soup is ladled for noon-day meal at the rural school of Fazenda Nova Granja. Kitchen was modernized according to ACAR instructions and sanitary food preparation practiced outlined. 34. Pre-school children meet five mornings a week for breakfast, games, and a session of teeth brushing and hair combing at the community center of the Itau cement industry in Minas Gerais. ACAR organized this community center and home visiting program which aids the 150 laborer farm families at the factory settlement. The factory pays for operating expenses and salaries of two full time supervisors trained by ACAR.
    - ACAR, Lagoa Santa, Agriculture, Prints: 5 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      1. Supervisor Pedro Morais assists borrower Jose Alvarenga in spraying his cattle for "bernes" and ticks. Cattle are badly infested and for better results should be sprayed monthly. The spray pump is ACAR property, recently introduced and proving successful in combating these parasites. 2. Supervisor Pedro Morais examining an injury of a hog of borrower Antonio Adao to determine the treatment required. 3. Garlic is one of the principal cash crops of Antonio Adao, ACAR borrower. The children (3 more, not in picture) provide most of the labor for cultivation by hand method. 4. Supervisor Pedro Morais discusses with the brother-in-law of Alcides Francisco Alves (borrower) the harvest of their first hybrid corn. 5. The wife of Antonio Adao, borrower, and four of his children discussing disease found in the vegetables. Supervision is given on the treatment of disease which is their first opportunity for such instruction.
    - ACAR, Lagoa Santa, Gardening, Prints: 1 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      6. The wife and child of borrower Antonio Adao, cultivating their garden which was greatly enlarged this year. Farmer Adao's loan was for repairing his home, building a sanitation toilet and labor for his crops. This picture was taken during the dry season when water must be provided by irrigation.
    - ACAR, Lagoa Santa, Sanitation, Prints: 2 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      7. The wife of Jose Alvarenga, borrower, is now boiling all of her drinking water, since the children were found to be suffering from worms and have received treatment from the ACAR doctor. 8. The kitchen of the wife of Antonio Adao is rather typical of the low-income family. The stove will be repaired, then the wall cleaned of smoke and grime, and a shelf built to accommodate pots and pans, etc. The first step was to start the family boiling water used for drinking and washing dishes.
    - ACAR, Minas Gerais, Agriculture, Prints: 20 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      1. No caption. 2. No caption. 3. No caption. 4. No caption. 5. No caption. 6. No caption. 7. No caption. 8. ACAR agronomist teaches farmers how to stop erosion on fields not planted on contour. 9. AGAR agronomist, Geraldo Machado, checks Joao Bernardez's coffee plantation where he has supervised the planning of pork beans for green fertilizer. Bernardez's neighbor (center) asks for seed and planting advice to try out this method on his own farm. 10. Irrigation via hand method. Common in Minas. This method is costly and inefficient and is being replaced on ACAR financed farms by the furrow method. 11. Throwing water by hand over the land to irrigate an onion patch which has been recently planted. This must be done daily during the dry season. 12. Common system of irrigation used in Minas. Water is lead over the land in small canals and t hen thrown by hand to cover the land. 13. Showing Dr. Euclides in the center, and the ACAR agronomist and technician on each side examining the hybrid corn which was financed by ACAR. 14. Typical irrigation canal used in central part of Minas. Much is being done to improve the irrigation system of borrowers. 15. This experimental plot may have discovered that cowpeas are almost equal in value to a long used crop called hog beans; cowpeas are used for both food and feed whereas hog beans have no value except to turn under. 16. Manure (compost) being applied to land. This is used only for truck crops in dry season. Farmers are being educated to the value of manure and compost. 17. Another ACAR agronomist in the hybrid cairn field of a borrower. This is the first year for hybrid corn in the territory and the farmers are pleased with the results. 18. Another view of the corn experiment plot in Curvelo. This is on the farm of the president of the ACAR Board of Directors. 19. A view of one of our three experimental plots for testing various varieties of corn, legumes and their response to various fertilizers. 20. Type of on-the-farm transport used in Minas.
    - ACAR, Minas Gerais, Gardening, Prints: 1 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      21. A satisfied farmer planting eucalyptus.
    - ACAR, Minas Gerais, Miscellaneous, Prints: 32 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      22. - 41. No caption. 42. Joao Bernardez Buena, a borrower under the supervised credit program of the Associacao de Credito e Assistencia Rural (ACAR) at Eloi Mendes, Minas Gerais, is optimistic about production on his hillside coffee fazenda. Intensive soil conservation, fertilization of trees and control of coffee worm, with the help of the ACAR agronomist, have already improved his trees and increased harvests. 43. Antonio de Paulo Lima is a borrower under the supervised credit program of ACAR at Eloi Mendes, Minas Gerais. With ACAR's technical help, Antonio is getting more production from his coffee trees, more milk from his herd of cattle. 44. Grain farmer Geraldino Caetano da Costa of Pedro Leopoldo, Minas Gerais gets advice on rice planting from Pedro Menezes, agronomist for ACAR. 45. Morro da Garca (concentration of borrowers). In foreground lives a borrower. Cameraman standing where by ACAR and the Government cooperation we expect a garden to be established to give civic pride a small encouragement. 46. Morro da Graca (location of a large group of borrowers). The main city drinking and washing water source during the rainy season. Looking toward the mountain of same name. 47. Morro da Garca. Main street one of the more densely populated sections. 48. New jeeps for ACAR field work on their way from Rip de Janeiro to Belo Horizonte. 49. New jeeps for ACAR field work on their way from Rip de Janeiro to Belo Horizonte. 50. New jeeps for ACAR field work on their way from Rip de Janeiro to Belo Horizonte. 51. New jeeps for ACAR field work on their way from Rip de Janeiro to Belo Horizonte. 52. No caption. 53. No caption.
    - ACAR, Minas Gerais, Nutrition, Prints: 2 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      54. No caption. 55. No caption.
    - ACAR, Minas Gerais, Sanitation, Prints: 1 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      56. A sanitary privy of the best type at the house of borrower Virginio Jose Ribeiro.
    - ACAR, Minas Gerais, Training School at Vicosa University, 1952; Prints: 41 (Box 3, Folder 53)
      57. ACAR agronomists must be in a position to help the farmer solve his daily problems, one of which is tick control. This photo shows candidate Afranio dos Santos Anjo, of Uberaba, spraying an animal. Watching the operation are (l to r) Dr. Anibal Torres, head of the Veterinary Department of the ESAV, and students Abel de Carvalho, of Lavras; and Anibal Prates, of Teofilo Ontoni. 58. Study of cattle treatment is essential in the ACAR training course, so that agronomists will be able to diagnose, control, and cure diseases. In the abovecattle to diagnose tuberculosis if present. From left to right appear Dr. Anibal Torres, head of the Veterinary Department of the ESAV; Abel de Carbalho, or Larvas, giving the injection; Anibal Prates, of Teofilo Ontoni, holding animal's tail; and Afranio dos Santos Anjo, of Uberaba. 59. No caption. 60. Speakers and honored guests at the ceremony marking completion of the 1952 training course for agronomists and home supervisors sponsored jointly by ACAR and the Rural University of Minas Gerais. Seated left to right: Miss Sue Taylor, consultant to AIA; Walter L. Crawford, director of ACAR; Joaquim Matoso, dean of the University's School of Agri.; Joaquim Braga, rector of the Rural University; Tristao da Cunha, State Secretary of Agri.; Joao Napoleon de Andrade, president of ACAR; and Euclides Martins, ACAR agronomist. 61. ACAR President Joao Napoleon de Andrades speaks at award presentation ceremony marking completion of 1952 training course sponsored jointly by ACAR and the Rural University of Minas Gerais at Vicosa. Seated is Euclides Martins, ACAR agronomist. 62. Display of simple but attractive furniture made by women students learning how to be home supervisors during ACAR's 1952 training course held at the Rural University of Minas Gerais, Vicosa. 63. Partial display of nutrition and health posters made by women students learning to be home supervisors at ACAR's 1952 training course held at the Rural University of Minas Gerais, Vicosa. 64. Partial display of nutrition and health posters made by women students learning to be home supervisors at ACAR's 1952 training course held at the Rural University of Minas Gerais, Vicosa. 65. Student agronomist milking at ACAR's 1952 training school held in cooperation with the Rural University. 66. Privy built by men students at ACAR's training school. 67. View of chicken house built by men students at ACAR's training school. 68. View of chicken house built by men students at ACAR's training school. 69. Candidates for the position of ACAR specialists build a chicken house. 70. Students, some of them future agronomists, make screen wire for fences, chicken houses, etc. 71. No caption. 72. These girls are learning to make furniture at ACAR's training school so they will be able to teach farmers' wives simple methods of home improvement. 73. Girl students of the ACAR course are instructed in tomato culture. 74. Students paint wardrobe which they made themselves in carpentry class of ACAR's 1952 Training School. 75. Students get instruction in milking at ACAR's 1952 training school held at the Rural University of Minas Gerais for future ACAR home economists and agronomists. 76. Dr. Amaury de Silveira, of Brazil's Department of Agricultural Information, teached vinegar-making to students of ACAR's 1952 training course held cooperatively with the Rural University. 77. Students learn care of farm animals at ACAR's training school for future home economists. 78. Girl enrolled in ACAR's training course learns about preserving eggs from Sue Taylor, American home economics specialist, formerly an ACAR staff member. 79. Even though a farmer's wife does not own a sewing machine, she can always borrow one from a neighbor's house or from the ACAR sponsored rural community center. Candidates for the position of ACAR home supervisor learn the intricacies of the sewing machine from Miss Lydia O'Farrell (seated, back of the camera). Standing against the wall is Miss Sue Taylor, American technician with wide experience in work in rural areas, head of the ACAR home supervisors. 80. Girl students in the ACAR training course must be proficient in sewing, so that they can instruct farmers' wives. 81. Some of the ACAR students here learn how to make simple furniture. They will later be able to pass on this knowledge to rural worker's families. 82. All students of the ACAR training course must know the basic principles of rural economy. Most of the students appear in the above photo, together with Prof. Edson Potsch Guimaraes, head of the Department of Rural Economy of the ESAV, giving a lecture. 83. ACAR candidates take courses on fundamental principles of poultry raising from Professor Nirman, of the Poultry Department of the ESAV. 84. Solid knowledge of preparing good and nutritious food is essential to all home supervisors. Housewives in rural areas in Minas Gerais, at first reluctant to change their diets, are gradually learning that with planned and varied menus they can improve the health of their families. 85. Every ACAR home supervisor must be experienced in hand-work. Hundreds of farmer's wives and daughters in Minas have learned to make simple and fancy articles that they previously bought in stores or went without. 86. ACAR home supervisors must be able to teach farmers' families how to grow vegetables, and what types should be planted so that they will have a balanced diet. In the above photo, Joao Torres Filho, agricultural technician in charge of the Horticulture Department of the Rural University of Minas Gerais supervises the work of two ACAR candidates, Miss Hilda Matoso Guimaraes (left), of work of two ACAR candidates. 87. Students drilling a well at ACAR's training school held at the Rural University of Minas Gerais, in 1952. 88. Girls practice milking at ACAR's 1952 training school held at the Rural University of Minas Gerais, Vicosa, for future home economists and agronomists. 89. Two promising candidates for the position of ACAR home supervisors are Miss Eunice Haddad (left), of Lavras, and Glaucia Soares (right), of Belo Horizonte. In this photo they are planning pieces of wood for a washboard. 90. Students learn to make and bottle tomato juice as part of course for future home economists at ACAR's training school. 91. Bottling tomato juice and using capping machine in ACAR's 1952 training school. 92. Students learn to make and cover mattresses in the course for future home economists at ACAR's training school held at the Rural University. 93. Members of an ACAR 4-S club sell vegetables they produced as a gardening project at a rented market stall in town of Vigosa. 94. ACAR's course at the Rural University of Minas Gerais aimed at practical training for home supervisors. At left, Mrs. Katharine Kenner, American teacher at the home economics school there, points out the best methods for washing clothes for longer wear. 95. Future home economists learn to make macaroni as a part of ACAR's 1952 training school held at the Rural University. 96. Home supervisors learn to make simple furniture, a technique they will later pass on to farm families, in ACAR's training course at the Rural Univ. 97. Home supervisors practice making cement floor blocks in a training course at the Rural Univ. as Aleta McDowell, head of ACAR's home economics department looks on.
    - ACAR, Minas Gerais, Training School at Vicosa University, 1952; Prints: 33 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      98. - 130. Captions included with photographs.
    - ACAR, Minas Gerais, 4-S Club, Prints: 9 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      131. 4-S Club members during the First State 4-S Club Convention held in Minas Gerais in 1962. 132. Secretary of Agriculture presents award to a 4-S Club member during the State 4-S Club Convention. 133. 4-S Club member giving demonstration on the control of parasites on livestock. 134. View in visitors at the 4-S Club Exposition during the State 4-S Club Convention. 135. Secretary of Agriculture, Dr. Roberto Rezende and ACAR President, Dr. Joao Napoleao de Andrade, present trophy to the state corn contest winner. 136. Governor Magalhaes Pinto congratulates 4-S club members during the opening ceremonies of the State 4-S Club Convention. 137. ACAR- Goias Executive Secretary, Dr. Josias Luiz Guimaraes, signs agreement at National 4-S Club Committee office to receive Cr. $4.800.000 (cruzeiros) to be used as a rotating loan funds for club members. This money is part of the USAID/Brazil donation to the National 4-S Club Committee, earmarked for the creation of rural youth loan funds. 138. Donation to CNC-4S: Mr. I.R. Hubbard of the Sears Roebuck Foundation of Chicago and Sr. JV Ruy Barbosa of Sears Roebuck do Brasil S/A, agreed to apply the $1,000 dollars to Heifer Project donation to the 4-S Community Development Project. This money was donated to the National 4-S Club Committee. 139. Ford Motor do Brazil: Visit of Mr. John C. Goulden to CNC-4S to present check of Cr $2.800.000 (cruzeiros) for 1966 activities.
    - ACAR, Mucambeiro, Administration, Prints: 3 (Box 3, Folder 56)